so remember that we need the load-linked
and the store conditional to behave like
a single atomic instruction so that
writes by other processors cannot come
in between them without us knowing well
this is how it happens we do a load link
from a lock variable to r1 and then we
do a store conditional of r2 into the
lock variable and what we need is that
if the load link finds the lock
available and we try to do a store
conditional then the store conditional
should only succeed if the lock is still
available at the time we try that if
somebody else has written into the lock
then store conditional needs to fail and
the key for that is that if we snoop a
right to lock var at any time we put a
zero in the link register so if the load
link loads the lock variable and we see
that it's free and we try to do a store
conditional but somebody beats us to it
then the store will fail because it will
observe that the link register doesn't
match the address of the lock wire so
the load-linked store conditional really
are relying on the coherence where we
observe right by others to make sure
that if the store conditional succeeds
it can guarantee that nobody else
grabbed a lock between when we check the
lock and when we think we grabbed it
really by writing a busy value into it
now note that the load-linked store
conditional are atomic by themselves we
don't need actually to use a lock to
make this atomic so some of the critical
sections that would just lock something
increment a variable and then unlock the
lock can now directly be implemented
using load link and store conditional on
the variable itself by load linking the
variable itself into r1 incrementing r1
store conditional of r1 back into the
variable and now we need to check if the
r1 as a result of the store conditional
became a 0 in which case somebody else
was trying to do the same thing
and we didn't succeed in doing this
atomically in which case we just try
again so eventually we will succeed in
this we will load and we will manage to
store before somebody else beats us to
it so if another thread is doing the
exact same thing here let's say we both
load now both of us linked to the
variable we both increment we both
stores whoever does the first store will
succeed whoever does the second store is
going to fail because by that time their
link is broken by the first store so
that's how for example we can do atomic
increments and all sorts of other things
that involve only one memory location
so very simple critical sections like
this can actually be directly implement
it with load-linked store conditional
without even needing locks anymore we
can use load link and store conditional
directly on the variable itself and we
no longer need an actual lock around it
for more complicated critical sections
such as those that access multiple
variables however load-linked store
conditional doesn't work well but we can
still use load-linked store conditional
to actually implement the lock variable
here without needing complicated
algorithms